<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://fantasticdice.games/blog</id>
    <title>Fantastic Dice Blog</title>
    <updated>2022-06-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://fantasticdice.games/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Fantastic Dice Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://fantasticdice.games/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Version 1 Release]]></title>
        <id>version-1</id>
        <link href="https://fantasticdice.games/blog/version-1"/>
        <updated>2022-06-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Big announcement. Version 1.0 has been released! The "last few things" took longer than expected. I really wanted to rework how themes were handled internally so different dice models could be used. I dug into supporting "levels of detail", "HD textures", "mobile textures" and many other things involved with over-engineering an idea. I'm happy with what I settled on which accomplishes the original goal of supporting different dice models.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Big announcement. <strong>Version 1.0 has been released!</strong> The "last few things" took longer than expected. I really wanted to rework how themes were handled internally so different dice models could be used. I dug into supporting "levels of detail", "HD textures", "mobile textures" and many other things involved with over-engineering an idea. I'm happy with what I settled on which accomplishes the original goal of supporting different dice models. </p><p>Now, <a href="https://github.com/3d-dice/dice-box" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@3d-dice/dice-box</a> only ships with the 'default' dice theme. All other themes I've develop have been moved into their own project at <a href="https://github.com/3d-dice/dice-themes" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@3d-dice/dice-themes</a>. This way, users can grab the themes they want and simply drop them into their themes folder. I even made a few custom color themes that really utilize the alpha channel in the diffuse texture. I was able to crete both color configurable textures that had a gritty overlay with the numbers. Check out the <a href="https://github.com/3d-dice/dice-themes/tree/main/themes/rust" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rust</a> and <a href="https://github.com/3d-dice/dice-themes/tree/main/themes/rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rock</a> themes if you're interested.</p><p>One of the hangups in my "last few things" was discovering that the dice models I had purchased from <a href="https://sketchfab.com/search?q=dice&amp;type=models" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sketchfab</a> and <a href="https://www.cgtrader.com/3d-models?keywords=dice" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CG Trader</a> had royalty free licenses, but redistribution was not allowed. Finding good license free game dice was a problem. Thankfully, I had been collaborating with the dev team at <a href="https://questportal.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Quest Portal</a>. They recently implemented <code>dice-box</code> into their virtual table top platform. This was a great experience and helped to really test the project's overall viability and production readiness. More on that in another post. Anyway, the team at Quest Portal was kind enough to help me out with procuring some license free game dice models. They are now the 'default' set. The default set will soon have a couple of bonus dice, including a <code>d2</code> a <code>fate</code> die and a <code>d6</code> with pips. However, while I was waiting on those dice to be produced, I decided to learn how to make my own dice set as well. I really wanted to show off the ability to use wildly different dice models in the project.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Dice models in Blender" src="/assets/images/diceModels-mat-wireframe-3daaba90c8f4b816b83eca865c7a94c9.jpg" width="1147" height="682" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>I learned soo much about <a href="https://www.blender.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Blender</a>. Thank goodness for YouTube. While it was a struggle, I was finally able to create two sets of 3D dice models. One is the "smooth" set and the other is the "gemstone" set. Carving the numbers out of the faces and then generating proper normal maps was a real struggle. After that the struggle continued as I attempted to create smooth low-poly assets, but I finally made it across the finish line. What we have now are two CC0 dice model assets.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Gemstone models in Blender" src="/assets/images/gemstone-wireframe-f8d8a25776d1eebcc0d27563a6c79402.jpg" width="816" height="539" class="img_ev3q"></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="some-other-great-features-in-10">Some other great features in 1.0<a class="hash-link" href="#some-other-great-features-in-10" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><ul><li>New config option for illumination level</li><li>New config option for shadow transparency</li><li>A truly random auto-generated fallback for non-standard/unsupported dice such as <code>d5</code></li><li>New config option to suspend the 3D animation and just get the random numbers (using the new random auto-generated fallback)</li><li>Support for <code>fate</code> dice</li><li>Improved error catching and error messages</li><li>Multiple other bug fixes</li></ul><p>In order to avoid a wall of text, I'm going to wrap up here. There are many other new features that came with version 1.0. <a href="https://www.babylonjs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BabylonJS</a> finally did hit version 5.0. Yay! So this release will benefit from all the performance improvements in Babylon as well. I hope other devs find this project useful and that I'm able to continue to developing useful features.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Frank Ali</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/frankieali</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="chat" term="chat"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Future Features]]></title>
        <id>future-features</id>
        <link href="https://fantasticdice.games/blog/future-features"/>
        <updated>2022-06-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is kind of like my own feature request post. There are a bunch of things that I still want to accomplish with this "side project" of mine. I'm going to leave some of those ideas here for future me.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is kind of like my own feature request post. There are a bunch of things that I still want to accomplish with this "side project" of mine. I'm going to leave some of those ideas here for future me.</p><ol><li><p>I just discovered <a href="https://rapier.rs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rapier.rs</a>. This is a new physics engine built using <a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rust</a> (and also documented using <a href="https://docusaurus.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Docusaurus</a> which this site uses as well). This looks like an amazing physics engine and something I certainly want to try. <a href="https://github.com/kripken/ammo.js/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AmmoJS</a> has been great, but development on the Bullet physics engine has slowed down and I think Rapier will be a quality successor. Check out this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SOFUgOkuHW8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">comparison on YouTube</a>. Right now, the only bottleneck I get during playback is from the Bullet physics simulation at around 400 dice which still isn't bad.</p></li><li><p>I would love to implement the sounds of dice rolling. I've been looking at other projects such as <a href="https://gitlab.com/riccisi/foundryvtt-dice-so-nice" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dice So Nice</a> and BabylonJS's own physics imposter implementation to see how I could implement the <code>onCollideEvent</code> to trigger sounds. Then there might even be different sound packages similar to Dice So Nice</p></li><li><p>Special Effects. The great thing about having a 3D engine and digital dice is that the sky is the limit when it comes to effects. I would love to see exploding dice actually explode. I would like to see some sort of effect when critical roles are triggered. I'd also like to try to implement animated materials, such as water, or even animated dice, like clockwork steampunk dice with moving gears. Take a look at the <a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/claim/dice/pride?icid_medium=ddb&amp;icid_source=article&amp;icid_campaign=dice-true-color&amp;icid_content=claim-true-color" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pride dice set from D&amp;D Beyond</a>. They get the idea.</p></li><li><p>An easy one to do would be to implement some simple post-processing in BabylonJS, such as motion blur, anti-aliasing, or other fun effects</p></li><li><p>On the "very near future" list is creating the <a href="https://www.fantasyflightgames.com/en/news/2017/6/27/genesys/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Genesys Dice</a> set. The new theme system in version 1.0 allows for rolling and identifying dice beyond their number type. So creating the Genesys set should be a good test for the theme system's flexibility. It will probably involve creating a new parser that I'm hoping to do as a true "plug-in". Soon to be followed by <a href="https://www.fantasyflightgames.com/en/legend-of-the-five-rings-roleplaying-game/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Legend of the Five Rings</a> which I also enjoy playing.</p></li><li><p>Also on the "very near future" list is an "additional dice" theme. I've got a set in the works that includes <code>d2</code>, <code>d14</code>, <code>d16</code>, <code>d18</code>, <code>d20</code>, <code>d24</code>, and <code>d30</code>. The modeling is almost complete. I still have to UV map everything which will be tricky. I really need to write a tutorial on how I make my themes from scratch.</p></li><li><p>I'd like to make a few more UI modules as well, such as:</p><ul><li><strong>last "x" rolls</strong> - records the last few notations</li><li><strong>theme picker</strong> - an easy interface for switching up themes and theme color</li><li><strong>quick dice picker</strong> - similar to the dice table on Roll20</li><li><strong>die roll distribution</strong> - roll results are saved to the browsers IndexedDB and processed to produce distribution graphs</li><li><strong>favorite rolls</strong> - save a few frequently used notations</li><li><strong>notation builder</strong> - a simple touch based ui to build complex notation</li></ul></li></ol><p>Well, that's it for now. Wish me luck.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Frank Ali</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/frankieali</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="chat" term="chat"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Pandemic Project is Almost Ready]]></title>
        <id>first-blog-post</id>
        <link href="https://fantasticdice.games/blog/first-blog-post"/>
        <updated>2022-03-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[It's been almost 2 years since I started digging into what it would take to build a fantastic dice roller that anyone could use in their own JavaScript projects. I've spend many hours optimizing this project so it would be both flexible and performant. I'm hopeful that it will gain traction and live up to expectations.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been almost 2 years since I started digging into what it would take to build a fantastic dice roller that <em>anyone</em> could use in their own JavaScript projects. I've spend many hours optimizing this project so it would be both flexible and performant. I'm hopeful that it will gain traction and live up to expectations.</p><p>I have some more exciting features in que before hitting the version 1.0 switch. I'm also waiting on <a href="https://www.babylonjs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BabylonJS</a> to hit <a href="https://forum.babylonjs.com/t/babylon-js-5-is-coming/26750" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">version 5</a> this Spring.</p><p>This site will continue to be updated along the way.</p><p>Cheers!</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Frank Ali</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/frankieali</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="chat" term="chat"/>
    </entry>
</feed>